A Guide to the Records of the Blue Ridge Disability Services Board, 1992-2009
Augusta County Historical Society
Augusta County Historical Society
Records of the Blue Ridge Disability Services Board, 1992-2009
Augusta County Historical Society
2019.0028
10 boxes, 4 ft., 8.5 in.
Blue Ridge Disability Services Board
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Marie Overstreet, a resident of Stuarts Draft, donated three boxes of files from the Blue Ridge Disability Services Board to the Augusta County Historical Society on February 11, 2014. She was a board member of the agency from 2002 to 2008.
Agency History
The Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA) was signed into law by President George H.W. Bush on July 26, 1990.
That same year, the Virginia General Assembly created the Disability Commission to evaluate services and programs for people with disabilities.
The 1992 report by the Disability Commission resulted in legislation mandating the development of Disability Services Boards (DSBs) to assist localities in identifying and addressing the needs of persons with physical and sensory disabilities in their communities, and a grant program, the Rehabilitative Services Incentive Fund.
As a result of this legislation and the report, the Virginia Department of Rehabilitative Services created regional disability boards. The DSBs were constituted to form partnerships of consumers, local governments, and businesses to increase access and develop consumer-oriented, community-based services for people with disabilities.
Funding for the DSBs was allocated yearly by the Virginia General Assembly. Some boards also received administrative funds or staff support from their local governments. Boards also received funds, either from their local government or the sub-grantees, to match the state Rehabilitative Services Incentive Fund dollars.
The Blue Ridge DSB was originally constituted to serve the counties of Augusta and Rockingham and the City of Harrisonburg. The City of Staunton was later added to its area of service.
The Operating Procedures for the DSB state: "This body will be known as the Blue Ridge Disability Services Board, hereafter referred to as the DSB as set forth in Section 51.5-47 of the Code of Virginia. The purpose of the DSB is to provide input to state and local agencies on service needs and priorities of persons with physical and sensory disabilities; to provide information and resource referral to local governments regarding the Americans with Disabilities Act; and to provide such other assistance and advice to local governments as may be requested."
Board members were appointed by the governing bodies of the constituent jurisdictions. The operating procedures set forth details regarding board members and their terms, standing committees, liaisons, meetings, officers, duties and responsibilities.
The Blue Ridge Disability Services Board disbanded in May 2009 due to lack of funding.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 10 boxes of materials. They contain administrative records, board meeting minutes, various reports, financial and personnel documents, correspondence, information on projects, and documentation of Rehabilitative Services Incentive Fund (RSIF) grants. The records date from 1992 to 2009.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in ten series.
Contents List
- Series 1: Administrative
  - Bylaws & operating procedures, 1992-1997 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Bylaws & operating procedures, 2001-2008 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Memo of Understanding, 2000 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Disability Services Boards member handbook, 2007 (Box-folder 1-4)
- Series 2: Membership
  - Membership (Box-folder 1-5)
- Series 3: Minutes - Board Meetings
  - 1993 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - 1994 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - 1995 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - 1996 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - 1997 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - 1998 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - 1999 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - 2000 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - 2001 (Box-folder 1-14)
  - 2002 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - 2003 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - 2004 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - 2005 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - 2006 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - 2007 (Box-folder 1-20)
  - [2008 is missing]
  - 2009 (Box-folder 1-21)
- Series 4: Reports
  - Quarterly Report, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 2-22)
  - Quarterly Report, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 2-23)
  - Quarterly Report, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 2-24)
  - Quarterly Report, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 2-25)
  - Quarterly Report, 2004-2005 (Box-folder 2-26)
  - Quarterly Report, 2005-2006 (Box-folder 2-27)
  - Quarterly Report, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 2-28)
  - Quarterly Report, 2007-2008 (Box-folder 2-29)
  - Quarterly Report, 2008-2009 (Box-folder 2-30)
  - Staff Liaison Report, 1993 (Box-folder 2-31 to 2-33)
  - Staff Liaison Report, 1994 (Box-folder 2-34 to 2-36)
  - Staff Liaison Report, 1995 (Box-folder 2-37 to 2-39)
  - Staff Liaison Report, 1996 (Box-folder 3-40 to 3-41)
  - Staff Liaison Report, 1997 (Box-folder 3-42 to 3-43)
  - Staff Liaison Report, 1998 (Box-folder 3-44 to 3-45)
  - Staff Liaison Report, 1999 (Box-folder 3-46)
  - Staff Support Activity Reports, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 3-47)
  - Staff Support Activity Reports, 2008-2009 (Box-folder 3-48)
  - Needs Assessment Report, 1993 (Box-folder 4-49)
  - Needs Assessment Report, 1995 (Box-folder 4-50)
  - Needs Assessment Report, 1997 & 1999 update (Box-folder 4-51)
  - Needs Assessment Report, 2003 (Box-folder 4-52)
  - Needs Assessment Report, 2006 (Box-folder 453)
  - Needs Assessment Report, 2008 (Box-folder 4-54)
  - Strategic Plan, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 4-55)
  - DSB System evaluative review, 2007 (Box-folder 4-56)
  - Unmet needs questionnaire, 2002 (Box-folder 4-57)
  - DSB office inventory, 2007-2009 (Box-folder 4-58)
  - Disability Among Virginians, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 4-59)
  - Healthy Community Assessment, 2006 (Box-folder 4-60)
- Series 5: Financial
  - Financial reports, 2008-2009 (Box-folder 5-61)
  - Pay records (Box-folder 5-62)
  - Bills, 2008 (Box-folder 5-63)
  - Bills, 2009 (Box-folder 5-64)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 5-65)
  - Funds reimbursement, FY 2009 (Box-folder 5-66)
  - Equipment purchases (Box-folder 5-67)
  - Liability insurance policy (Box-folder 5-68)
- Series 6: Personnel
  - Administrative Assistant position (Box-folder 5-69)
  - Staff Support Handbook (Box-folder 5-70)
- Series 7: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, Augusta County (Box-folder 6-71)
  - Correspondence, Staunton (Box-folder 6-72)
  - Correspondence, Rockingham County (Box-folder 6-73)
  - Correspondence, Harrisonburg (Box-folder 6-74)
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous (Box-folder 6-75)
- Series 8: Projects
  - Assistive Technology Fair, 2003 (Box-folder 6-76)
  - Brenda Papke Memorial Sensory Garden, 2007 (Box-folder 6-77)
  - Disability Friendly Businesses (Box-folder 6-78)
  - ADA Customer Friendly Award (Box-folder 6-79)
  - Projects Planning, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 6-80)
  - Scrapbook (Box-folder 6-81)
  - Scrapbook (Box-folder 6-82)
  - Public hearing, 2002 (Box-folder 6-83)
  - Website (Box-folder 6-84)
- Series 9: Organizations
  - Virginia Association of DSBs, 2008 (Box-folder 6-85)
  - Valley Associates for Independent Living (Box-folder 6-86)
  - VATS Conference, 2000 (Box-folder 6-87)
  - Bath-Highland DSB (Box-folder 6-88)
- Series 10: Rehabilitative Services Incentive Funds (RSIF) Grants
  - RSIF Grant, FY 1996 (Box-folder 7-89)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 1997 (Box-folder 7-90)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 1998 (Box-folder 7-91 to 7-92)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 1999 (Box-folder 7-93)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 2000 (Box-folder 7-94)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 2001 (Box-folder 7-95 to 7-98)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 2002 (Box-folder 8-99 to 8-104)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 2003 (Box-folder 8-105 to 8-108)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 2004 (Box-folder 9-109 to 9-110)
  - RSIF Grant, Volunteer Payee Program, 2002-2004 (Box-folder 9-111)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 2005 (Box-folder 9-112)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 2006 (Box-folder 9-113)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 2007 (Box-folder 9-114)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 2008 (Box-folder 9-115 to 9-117, Box-folder 10-118 to 10-121)
  - RSIF Grant, FY 2009 (Box-folder 10-122 to 10-127)